Finding Aid for Eva Jessye Collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Eva Jessye Collection 1927-1992 1935-1980
Jessye, Eva
2009184 Aa 2
The Eva Jessye collection contains the personal papers and collected material of Eva Jessye, a prominent choral director, composer, arranger, writer, poet, actress and African American Music historian. Born in Coffeyville, Kansas in 1895, Jessye gained prominence as the conductor for Original Dixie Jubilee Singers, and as choral director for Gertrude Stein and Virgil Thomson's opera Four Saint in Three Acts. Jessye was the choral director for the original production (and many subsequent productions) of Porgy and Bess. The collection includes both materials from Jessye's personal and professional life as well as collected material which documents prominent African Americans.
14 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in September 2008 through the Center for AfroAmerican and African Studies (donor no. 10110 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Eva Jessye was born in Coffeyville, Kansas on January 20, 1895. She attended Western University and Langston University, receiving her BA in 1919. After a number of teaching positions in Baltimore (Morgan College, 1919) and Tulahassee (1920-1925), Oklahoma, Jessye worked for the Baltimore newspaper The Afro-American.
Moving to New York, she formed a small singing group that came to the attention of African American composer Will Marion Cook. Cook became her mentor, tutoring her in music theory and music management. In 1926 Jessye organized the Original Dixie Jubilee Singers, which performed regularly on radio shows such as "The Major Bowes Family Radio Hour" and "The General Motors Hour." In 1929 Jessye and the Original Dixie Jubilee Singers went to Hollywood and appeared in King Vidor's all-black film Hallelujah. Because the name "Dixie Jubilee Singers" was being appropriated by many other choirs, her choir's name was changed to the Eva Jessye Choir.
In 1934 Jessye became the choir director of Gertrude Stein and Virgil Thomson's work Four Saint in Three Acts. In 1935, Jessye became the choral director for the premiere production of George Gershwin's opera Porgy and Bess. Jessye toured the United States, Europe, the Soviet Union and New Zealand performing Porgy and Bess and was associated with countless other productions worldwide. Jessye acted as an adviser for the BBC's For the Children: Huckleberry Finn and Down in the Valley (1952) and performed in the 1959 Hallmark Hall of Fame production of Kiss Me Kate. In 1963, her choir was designated the official chorus of the civil rights march on Washington, DC, organized by Martin Luther King, Jr.
Throughout Jessye's career she appeared in several motion pictures including Hallelujah (1929) (where she was also the Musical Director), Black Like Me (1964) and Slaves (1969) with Stephen Boyd and Ossie Davis.
Jessye came to the University of Michigan in 1974. With the encouragement of Dean Willis Paterson, she established the Eva Jessye Afro-American Music Collection which is the basis for the present collection. From 1977 to 1981 she was an Artist in-Residence at Pittsburg State University in Kansas where she created a similar Eva Jessye Collection (see: http://library.pittstate.edu/spcool/ndxjessye.html). Jessye was honored by many universities, states and cities for her life achievements and received honorary doctorates from the University of Michigan School of Music, Eastern Michigan University and Glassboro State College.
Dr. Eva Jessye died on February 21, 1992, at the age of 97 in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
__________________________________
Sources Consulted:
http://www.umich.edu/~afroammu/jessye.html (as of April 21, 2009)
The Eva Jessye Collection, AXE-Special Collections. (n.d.) Retrieved April 21, 2005, from: http://library.pittstate.edu/spcool/ndxjessye.html/. Leonard H. Axe Library, Pittsburg State University, Pittsburg, Kansas
The Eva Jessye Collection contains both personal papers of Jessye, as well as material collected by Jessye. The Eva Jessye collection is made up of twelve series: Biographical; Correspondence; Eva Jessye Choir; Writings (Performances, Poetry and Speeches); Music; Productions; Eva Jessye Programs; Collected Programs; Eva Jessye Clippings; Black History Clippings; Photographs; and Awards and Certificates.
Subjects:
African American composers.; African American theater.; African American women musicians.; African Americans--Music.; Conductors (Music)--United States.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937--Porgy and Bess.; Jessye, Eva, 1895-1992.; Spirituals (Songs); Women musicians.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Actors.; Actresses.; African American actors.; African American actresses.; African American theater.; African American women musicians.; African Americans--Composers.; African Americans--Music.; African Americans--Music.; African Americans--Women.; Composers.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937--Porgy and Bess.; Jessye, Eva, 1895-1992.; Musicians--United States.; Theatrical productions--United States.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series (0.25 linear feet) consists of personal documents, such as Jessye's Equity contract, a sparsely notated travel diary, as well as personal reflections and notes on a range of topics including her experiences performing Porgy and Bess and memories of touring and traveling the world.
  - Celebration of the Life of Eva Jessye (Box 1)
  - Equity Contract (Box 1)
  - Inoculation and Vaccination documents (Box 1)
  - Local Detroit Contact Book (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - "My Trip" Book (Box 1)
  - Stocks (Box 1)
  - Personal Reflections and Information (Box 1)
  - Notes
    - Backstage Chatter (Box 1)
    - Balancing the Books (Box 1)
    - Discrimination (Box 1)
    - Drama that is Harlem Still Survives (Fragments) (Box 1)
    - Early Years (Box 1)
    - Eva Jessye (Box 1)
    - "Fill Up the Saucer" (Box 1)
    - Meeting Lucky Roberts: Willie the Lion Smith description (Box 1)
    - Notes and Sayings (Box 1)
    - Personal Reflections (Box 1)
    - Productions (Box 1)
    - Porgy and Bess
      - Addresses for New York production (Box 1)
      - Career and Personages in Porgy and Bess (Box 1)
      - Names of Principals from 1930 on (Box 1)
      - Reviews and Rehearsals (Dallas, Chicago, DC) 1952 (Box 1)
      - Roles and Material (Box 1)
      - Tours and Happenings (Box 1)
      - Tours in Israel (Box 1)
    - Red Man in OK (Box 1)
    - Sigmund Spaeth (Box 1)
    - Slave Composers who, what, how and when sayings (Box 1)
    - Spivy, Contempt of Eva Jessye (Box 1)
    - Travel: South America and Rome (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (0.75 linear feet) contains personal and professional correspondence from 1927 to 1992. The first subseries organizes correspondence alphabetically by author, while the second subseries is organized by year. Undated and unknown sender items as well as thank-you notes and postcards are collected at the end of the series. Of special interest are letters from Jessye to friends and colleagues around the country. In these letters Jessye discusses putting on productions of Paradise Lost, of the creations and dedications of her collections and her experiences at Michigan and Pittsburg State. While most of the letters are originals, there are some reproductions of correspondence from Ira Gershwin, Langston Hughes and others.
  - By Individual
    - Bailey, Pearl (Box 1)
    - Dawson, William (Box 1)
    - Duncan, Todd (Box 1)
    - Easton, Harriet with a draft of her Autobiography (Box 1)
    - "Fill Up the Saucer" (Box 1)
    - Flusser, Beth (Box 1)
    - Gershwin, Ira (copies) (Box 1)
    - Goreau, Laurraine, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Hairston, Jester, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Huntley, Jobe (Box 1)
    - Jessye, Eva, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - King, Coretta Scott (Box 1)
    - Mitchell, Lofton (Box 1)
    - Nord, Paul (Box 1)
    - Parks, Gordon (Box 1)
    - Smith, Kay (Box 1)
    - Southern, Eileen (Box 1)
    - Vidor, King (Box 1)
    - Williams, Clyde (Box 1)
    - Williams, Ora, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Chronological
    - 1927-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977 (Box 1)
    - 1978 (Box 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - 1982 (Box 1)
    - 1983 (Box 1)
    - 1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
    - 1992 (Box 1)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Unknown Sender (Box 1)
  - Appreciation Notes (Box 1)
  - Thank you notes, holiday cards, postcards (Box 1)
  - Incomplete letters (Box 1)
- Eva Jessye Choir
  The Eva Jessye Choir series (0.2 linear feet) contains articles and reviews of the choir as well as advertisements, programs, and personnel lists of the group. Though it is a small series, it spans the life of the group from the 1920s to the 1960s. For photographs of the choir, see the Photographs series.
  - History and Recording Information (Box 2)
  - Advertisements (Box 2)
  - African Freedom Day 1960 (Box 2)
  - Baltimore Afro-American article 1934 (Box 2)
  - College Tour Material 1967 (Box 2)
  - Personnel List 1920s (Box 2)
  - Personnel List 1938 (Box 2)
  - Programs, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Picture (1930) (Box 2)
  - Reviews (Box 2)
- Writings (Performances, Poetry and Speeches)
  The Writings (Performances, Poetry and Speeches) series (0.5 linear feet) collects Jessye's production, poetry and speech output. All subseries are organized alphabetically by title. The production subseries includes performances for which she wrote or arranged the lyrics/script for the production. Jessye composed poetry for a number of occasions including odes to friends and colleagues and public celebrations and performances. Several of these poems are collected in the small pamphlet titled "Selected Poems." The Speeches subseries consists of copies and drafts of speeches from the 1970s and 1980s.
  - Performances
    - Christmas Program (Box 2)
    - Chronicle of Job
      - Program (Box 2)
      - Script (Box 2)
    - Gifts from the Altar
      - Script Drafts (Box 2)
      - Readings (Box 2)
    - The Star (Box 2)
    - This is Your Life (Box 2)
    - Wade in the Water (Box 2)
    - Western Star (Box 2)
  - Poetry
    - An "If" for Directors (Box 2)
    - As For the Afro-American (or Black Man) (Box 2)
    - As For the Presidency (Box 2)
    - Aunt Mae and Uncle A.K. (Box 2)
    - A Bag of Peanuts (Box 2)
    - The Builders (Box 2)
    - Caddy and the Coal Truck (Box 2)
    - Centennial Ode to African Methodism (Box 2)
    - Commentary Update (Box 2)
    - Curiosity (Box 2)
    - Epic of the Dolly Pearl (Box 2)
    - Epitaph for an Elderly Actress (Box 2)
    - Family Tree (Box 2)
    - A Fast Food Rap (Box 2)
    - Findings (Box 2)
    - For Teachers (Box 2)
    - Frederick Douglass (Box 2)
    - Gifts the Whole Year Long (Box 2)
    - The Girl Friday (Box 2)
    - Good Company (Box 2)
    - Goodies at the Gilberts (Box 2)
    - The Highway (Box 2)
    - Holdout to the End (Box 2)
    - Kansas Youth (Box 2)
    - Keep Me at It (Box 2)
    - Let it Alone (Box 2)
    - Lucky Friendship Seven (Box 2)
    - The Maestro (Box 2)
    - Make the Goal (Box 2)
    - Makers of the Spirituals (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - My Favorite Dish (Box 2)
    - My Past 50 Years (Box 2)
    - The Nurse (Box 2)
    - Old, Not so Gifted, and Black (Box 2)
    - Paean (Box 2)
    - Paen to San Diego (Box 2)
    - Pertinent Topics (Box 2)
    - Rap Dialogue (Box 2)
    - Ratings (Box 2)
    - Raves for the Slaves (Box 2)
    - Realization (Box 2)
    - Remembrance (Box 2)
    - A Salute (Box 2)
    - The Singer (Box 2)
    - Song of Freedom (Box 2)
    - The Source (Box 2)
    - Sparrow in Winter (Box 2)
    - Sunny Kansas (Box 2)
    - Thanksgiving to My Favorite Two (Box 2)
    - This Man (Box 2)
    - The Theatre (Box 2)
    - To a Preacher's Wife (Box 2)
    - To a Rosebud (Box 2)
    - To Romare Bearden (Box 2)
    - Values (Box 2)
    - Various Fragments, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Week Before Christmas (Box 2)
    - Selected Poems (Box 2)
    - Never Dies the Dream (Box 2)
    - Today is Ours (Box 2)
  - Speeches
    - From Vantage Point Ninety-One (Box 2)
    - Hortense Love Introduction 1978 (Box 2)
    - Introducing Leontyne Price (Box 2)
    - It's a Matter of Pride (Box 2)
    - Langston Hughes, His Works Do Follow Him 1981 (Box 2)
    - Never Dies the Dream (Box 2)
    - Olympiad of the Arts 1984 (Box 2)
    - Pittsburg State University 1979 (Box 2)
    - Salute to Duke Ellington (Box 2)
    - Various Fragments (Box 2)
- Music
  The Music series (0.2 linear feet) holds both published and manuscript sheet music that was composed, adapted, arranged and or edited by Jessye. Many of the pieces are arrangements of spirituals for small chorus groups. This series is arranged alphabetically by song title.
  - Black Joe, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - Bles' My Soul and' Gone, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - Goin' Back South, composed by Jessye (Box 2)
  - Got a Home At Las', arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - Hand Car Blues, composed by Jessye (Box 2)
  - He's Carried the Key and Gone Home, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - I Belong to that Band, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - I Can't Stay Away, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - I'm a Po' Lil' Orphan, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - I'se Mighty Tired, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - John Saw de Holy Numbah, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - March Down to Jordon, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - Move! Let me Shine, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - My Spirituals, compiled by Jessye (Box 2)
  - Pittsburg State University Alma Mater, Composed by Jessye (Box 2)
  - Rock Mt Sinai!, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - Sol' Away to Georgia, Composed by Jessye (Box 2)
  - Song of Freedom, Composed by Jessye (Box 2)
  - Spirit o' the Lord Done Fell on Me, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - Swing Low, Sweet Chariot, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - When Moses Smote the Water, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
  - When the Saints Go Matching In, arr. Jessye (Box 2)
- Productions
  The Productions series (1.1 linear feet) documents various dramatic and musical productions that Jessye worked on as a conductor, organizer, and choral director. The material is grouped by production title and holds various genres including scripts, vocal scores, programs, stage readings and instructions, and character/cast lists. Items of particular note include: Jessye's vocal score for the Four Saints opera; background and research material that went into creating The Old Flag Never Touched the Ground, a production composed by Jessye and based on the memoirs of William Carney, who fought in the Battle for Fort Sumter; extensive score, libretto and direction material for Jessye's adaptation of Milton's Paradise Lost and Regained; cast materials and scripts for the 1969 movie Slaves; and production material for Langston Hughes' musical Tambourines to Glory.
  - Ballad of Catfish Grimes, Libretto (Box 2)
  - Black Titan (Box 2)
  - Christmas Program, Script (Box 2)
  - The Clergy
    - Program (Box 2)
    - Reading Assignments (Box 2)
  - Dance Little David, Libretto (Box 2)
  - Digging the Ring, Libretto (Box 2)
  - Follow the Star, Script (Box 2)
  - Four Saints, Vocal Score (Box 2)
  - Give Away Jordon, Script (Box 2)
  - Hephestos and Force, Script (Box 2)
  - Hidden Faces, Script (Box 2)
  - Home to Harlem
    - Script (Box 2)
    - Characters (Box 2)
  - How Long Till Summer (Box 2)
  - In Memoriam to W.E.B. DuBois, Script (Box 2)
  - Kwamina, Script (Box 2)
  - Let the Chorus say Amen, Rehearsal Copy (Box 2)
  - Life of Christ, Narrator Script and Program (Box 2)
  - Lily of the Valley, Script (Box 2)
  - Lost in the Stars, Vocal Score (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - The Negro Soldier (Research and Script) (Box 3)
  - Oklahoma, Outlines (Box 3)
  - The Old Flag Never Touched the Ground
    - Background, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Music (Box 3)
    - NARA Letter (Box 3)
    - Review (Box 3)
  - Paradise Lost and Regained
    - Administrative Material (Box 3)
    - Score, Draft Notebook (Box 3)
    - Score, Choral (Box 3)
    - Score, Vocal (Box 3)
    - Score, Vocal Fragments 1978 (Box 3)
    - Libretto, Draft and Final Versions (Box 3)
    - Libretto, Notated, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Libretto Fragments, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Press Materials (Box 3)
    - Press Releases and Photo References (Box 3)
    - Programs (Box 3)
    - Scenes and Events (Box 3)
    - Scene List 1972 (Box 3)
  - Porgy and Bess
    - Vocal Score Copy (Box 3)
    - Vocal Score Fragments (Box 3)
  - Prophecy Nativity, Music (Box 3)
  - Projugal Son, Script (Box 3)
  - Prometheus Bound (Box 3)
  - Rebekkah, Script (Box 3)
  - River Gambler, Script (Box 3)
  - Roman Court-martial, Script (Box 3)
  - Slaves
    - Cast and Crew Schedules (Box 3)
    - Cast and Review (Box 3)
    - Programs and Clippings (Box 3)
    - Script, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Script Revisions (Box 3)
  - Simon the Fisherman, Music and Script (Box 3)
  - Tambourines to Glory
    - Cast Lists (Box 3)
    - Chorus Audition Lists (Box 3)
    - Folkways, Notes and Lyrics (Box 3)
    - Lyrics (Jessye Personal Copy) (Box 3)
    - Lyrics (Huntley Copy) (Box 3)
    - Lyrics, Duplicates (Box 3)
    - Music, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Musical Bridges List (Box 3)
    - Playbills (Box 3)
    - Reviews (Box 3)
    - Script (Box 3)
    - Script, Duplicate (Box 3)
    - Script, Excerpts (Box 3)
    - Songs by Character (Box 3)
  - Various Fragments, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Eva Jessye Programs
  The Eva Jessye Programs series (1.0 linear feet) collects programs for productions that Jessye was involved with. The bulk of the collection is programs for Porgy and Bess between 1935 and 1992 including tours of American Cities, universities and international productions. These programs are organized by data of performance with undated and unknown venue productions grouped at the end. The Other Programs subseries collects non- Porgy and Bess performances including musical concerts and dramatic productions. Included as outsized materials are a number of concert posters for events that Jessye was a part of or that were organized as fundraisers.
  - Porgy and Bess (Box 4)
    - Colonial Theatre 1935 (Box 4)
    - Majestic Theatre 1942 (Box 4)
    - Maplewood Theatre 1941 (Box 4)
    - Shubert Theatre 1941 (Box 4)
    - Cass Theatre 1943 (Box 4)
    - Tabor Theatre 1944 (Box 4)
    - War Memorial Opera House 1944 (Box 4)
    - Civic Opera House 1952 (Box 4)
    - Volksoper, Austria 1952 (Box 4)
    - Empire Theatre, Paris 1953 (Box 4)
    - Stoll Theatre, London 1953 (Box 4)
    - Ziegfeld Theatre 1953 (Box 4)
    - Ahmanson Theatre 1954 (Box 4)
    - Cass Theatre 1954 (Box 4)
    - Her Majesty's Theatre 1954 (Box 4)
    - Philharmonic Auditorium 1954 (Box 4)
    - Columbia 1955 (Box 4)
    - Santiago 1995 (Box 4)
    - Italy 1955 (Box 4)
    - Camden Country Music Fair 1958 (Box 4)
    - Niagara 1958 (Box 4)
    - Thistledown Race Track 1958 (Box 4)
    - Toronto 1958 (Box 4)
    - Valley Forge 1958 (Box 4)
    - Wostbury Music Fair 1958 (Box 4)
    - WPAT 1959 (Box 4)
    - New York City Center 1964 (Box 4)
    - Swope Park 1964 (Box 4)
    - Camden Country Music Fair 1965 (Box 4)
    - Carousel Theatre 1965 (Box 4)
    - Civic Arena 1965 (Box 4)
    - Civic Theatre 1965 (Box 4)
    - Coconut Grove 1965 (Box 4)
    - Oakdale 1965 (Box 4)
    - New Zealand 1965 (Box 4)
    - Painters Mill 1965 (Box 4)
    - Royal Aleyandra Theatre 1965 (Box 4)
    - Shady Grove 1965 (Box 4)
    - Storrowton 1965 (Box 4)
    - Westbury 1965 (Box 4)
    - Clowes Memorial Hall 1966 (Box 4)
    - Habima Theatre 1966 (Box 4)
    - Tel Aviv 1966 (Box 4)
    - Akron Civic Theatre 1967 (Box 4)
    - Atlanta Municipal Auditorium 1967 (Box 4)
    - Bushnell 1967 (Box 4)
    - Eastman Theatre 1967 (Box 4)
    - George Hall 1967 (Box 4)
    - Grove City 1967 (Box 4)
    - Hill Auditorium 1967 (Box 4)
    - Jesse H. Jones Hall 1967 (Box 4)
    - Indiana University 1967 (Box 4)
    - Kiel Opera House 1967 (Box 4)
    - Knoxville Civic Auditorium 1967 (Box 4)
    - Mason Auditorium 1967 (Box 4)
    - Michigan State University 1967 (Box 4)
    - Montreal Canada 1967 (Box 4)
    - Northern Illinois University 1967 (Box 4)
    - Ohio University 1967 (Box 4)
    - Palace Theatre 1967 (Box 4)
    - Saint Mary's College 1967 (Box 4)
    - Shyrock Auditorium 1967 (Box 4)
    - Stanley Theatre 1967 (Box 4)
    - Syracuse University 1967 (Box 4)
    - University of Connecticut 1967 (Box 4)
    - University of Florida 1967 (Box 4)
    - University of Illinois, Champaign 1967 (Box 4)
    - University of Vermont 1967 (Box 4)
    - Virginia State College 1967 (Box 4)
    - Wise State University 1967 (Box 4)
    - Turkey 1968 (Box 4)
    - South Carolina 1970 (Box 4)
    - Komische Opera House 1971 (Box 4)
    - Fort Worth 1972 (Box 4)
    - Memphis State University 1972 (Box 4)
    - Operetten Haus, Hamburg 1972 (Box 4)
    - Teatro Comunade 1972 (Box 4)
    - Teatro Grande Brescia 1972 (Box 4)
    - Teatro Verdi 1972 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan 1972 (Box 4)
    - Teatro Nacional, Lisbon 1973 (Box 4)
    - Teatro Nacional De S. Carlos 1973 (Box 4)
    - Detroit Opera House 1975 (Box 4)
    - Bengamine Franklin Jr. High, NJ 1976 (Box 4)
    - Houston Grand Opera 1976 (Box 4)
    - Krannert, IL 1976 (Box 4)
    - Louisiana State University 1976 (Box 4)
    - Arie Crown Theatre 1977 (Box 4)
    - Municipal Opera 1977 (Box 4)
    - Bryan City, 197- (Box 4)
    - Kingsbury Hall 1981 (Box 4)
    - Radio City Music Hall 1983 (Box 4)
    - Majestic Theatre 1985 (Box 4)
    - Kennedy Center DC 1987 (Box 4)
    - Royal Opera 1992 (Box 4)
    - Auditorio Nacional De Mexico undated (Box 4)
    - Royal Opera House undated (Box 4)
    - Various undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Various, Date and Venue Unknown, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - An American Voice Overview (Box 4)
    - A Candid Expose (Box 4)
    - Legacy of Porgy and Bess (Box 4)
  - Other Programs
    - Black Music Lecture 1978 (Box 4)
    - Black Titan (Box 4)
    - Black Woman Artists 1981 (Box 4)
    - Dallas, Yours and Mine (Box 4)
    - Eva Jessye's American Concert Ensemble 1957 (Box 4)
    - Eva Jessye University of Michigan Collection Exhibition 1973 (Box 4)
    - Facing the Rising Sun, 1975 (Box 4)
    - History of Nicodemus, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Incredible Diversity of Afro-American Music 1979 (Box 4)
    - Kansas, Yours and Mine (Box 4)
    - Le Moyne Owen Music Department Festival 1983 (Box 4)
    - Merit Awards Ceremony (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Concerts (Box 4)
    - Paradise Lost, 1974 (Box 4)
    - Pittsburg State University Master Class 1979 (Box 4)
    - Spiritual 1978 (Box 4)
    - Taft Bicentennial Committee 1975 (Box 4)
    - To The Teacher, With Love, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Western Star, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Oversized Posters (located in Box 14) (Box 4)
- Collected Programs
  The Collected Programs Series (1.0 linear feet) includes theatrical programs, concert programs, and lectures and memorials that Jessye attended but did not actively participate in. These items are alphabetically organized by production title.
  - Theatrical Programs
    - 70 Girls 70, 1971 (Box 5)
    - All God's Chillun Got Wings Lenox Hill (Box 5)
    - Alvin Ailey American Dance Theatre, Anta Theatre 1971 (Box 5)
    - Amen Corner, Ethel Barrymore Theatre (Box 5)
    - Andersonville Trial, Henry Miller's Theatre (Box 5)
    - Arsenic and Old Lace, Bronx (Box 5)
    - Arturo Ui, Lunt Fontanne, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Avon Long (Box 5)
    - The Balcony, Columbia (Box 5)
    - Ballad for Bimshire, Mayfair Theatre (Box 5)
    - Bicycle Ride to Nevada (Box 5)
    - Black Birds (Box 5)
    - Blues for Mr. Charlie (Box 5)